<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>No nevvs, but a letter to every body. Prescribed, to your truly beloved self; any where: so that you be not resolved to be, who and where you should not be; with care and speed, these be presented. / And subscribed, your daily orator at the throne of grace, R.W.</title>
            <author>R. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E526_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205656</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858753</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858753</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110811</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96054)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110811)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 82:E526[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>No nevvs, but a letter to every body. Prescribed, to your truly beloved self; any where: so that you be not resolved to be, who and where you should not be; with care and speed, these be presented. / And subscribed, your daily orator at the throne of grace, R.W.</title>
                  <author>R. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 162 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "October ye 6th 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1660 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110811:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>NO NEVVS, BUT A <hi>LETTER</hi> TO EVERY BODY. PRESCRIBED, To your truly Beloved Self; Any where: So that you be not reſolved to be, who and where you ſhould not be; With Care and Speed, theſe be preſented.</head>
            <head type="sub">And Subſcribed, Your daily Orator at the Throne of Grace, <hi>R. W.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Piſcator, niſi eam impoſuerit hamis eſcam, quam appetituros eſſe noverit Piſciculos; fine ſpe praedae moratur in Scopulo.</q>
               <bibl> 
                  <hi>Petr: Arb.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVIthout ſome (at leaſt ſeeming) inſolency; and little above the price of 2 d. nothing, (now) will be read. But pardon his preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in writing to all; ſince he faithfully and truly does (as he is commanded) in praying for all. Let him have leave to ſend to thee; who muſt ſend to GOD for thee; of what ſpirit ſoever thou art; who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dares nor can, exempt thee from his Prayers; who dares not but daily make uſe of the moſt pretious and Chriſtian Engliſh LITURGIE.</p>
            <p>So that (ſince <hi>Perſonall Treaties</hi> are ſo difficult) let me <hi>treat</hi> with thee, thus as I may. The ſubject is of moſt High and Generall Concernment; our <hi>Nationall Miſeries, Cauſes and Cures</hi> thereof. Nor can this <hi>Treaty</hi> be more beneficiall to any, then to thoſe who (without an hardened Heart) are moſt Averſe from it; or engaged againſt it, and the Conſcientious moments thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> concerning thoſe who are (now) the firſt in the eye of all; <hi>the two Houſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The two Houſes, &amp; 2. Oaths, &amp;c.</note> And firſt, it is worthy of Conſideration, <hi>whether or not,</hi> they have <hi>blaſphemed GOD and the King,</hi> by the foule ſins of <hi>Perjury</hi> and <hi>Treaſon?</hi> As having given unto GOD and the King, their Oaths for his <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and their <hi>Allegiance;</hi> But have made themſelves Supreme; impriſoning and denying to the King not onely his Native Rights; but alſo the poore comfort of Addreſſes (ſo much as by Letters) of Wiſe, Children, friends or ſervants. Whereas neither the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt worm, nor odiouſeſt Serpent in the Kingdom, by the Laws thereof, either is or ought to be ſouſed. And if ſo, who in Juſtice may make Addreſſes unto
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110811:2"/>them? who may give Credit unto them? or what Hopes can any man have from perſiſters in wilfull Perjury? or who may dare to be any wayes Aſſiſting, Aiding or of Councell, in moſt barbarous Treaſon? Such as ſhould not be ſo much as named among Heathens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CONCERNING PRIVILEDGES OF PARLIAMENT.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Priviledges of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> If they be ſo great as is pretended; It is great pitie, that ſome reaſonable and peaceable courſe is not taken for the manifeſtation of them, &amp; their juſt Grounds: When, whence, and How, they had their Beginnings, That men might underſtand How farre they are engaged to them; and how far they ought to engage for them. If in this point matters be clear; How comes it to paſſe, that in all this time care is not taken for the Anſwering of the <hi>FREEHOLDERS GRAND INQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EST?</hi> which (with other Books of that Nature) tels us of Sir <hi>Edw: Coke</hi> (no friend to the Prerogative) that in his whole Section of Parliamentary <hi>Priviledges</hi> He ſets down but one <hi>(viz. Freedom from Arreſts)</hi> and brings no proof for That.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Freedom of Speech</hi> (wherein GOD forbid that Blaſphemy and Treaſon ſhould be included) be one of them;
<note place="margin">Freedom of Speech.</note> How come ſo many to be ejected (daily by the prevailing Faction, as the winde ſits) out of both Houſes? Or how ſhall their mouthes be ſtopped, that Affirm, That for theſe many yeers, there hath been no Freedom for any thing but Blaſphemy and Treaſon, with their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants; The direct Contrarieties to all the Ten Commandments of GOD; either in the whole or a principall part of each? Or that the <hi>Priviledges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> have more need to be defended againſt themſelves, then againſt the King and the whole Kingdom beſides? Or that whereas the Army was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Parliaments Army; Now the Parliament is the Armies Parliament?</p>
            <p>It is likewiſe conſiderable,
<note place="margin">Invaſion of Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> 
               <hi>whether or no</hi> (as the Grandees have done by the reſt of the Members) the pretended Priviledge of the Houſe of Commons, hath (like <hi>Pharaohs lean kine</hi>) eaten up the Priviledges of the Houſe of Lords? If no; How comes it to paſſe, that (for the ſatisfaction of the world, and for the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Accuſed) punctuall Anſwers are not given (or Ordered) to the forecited Books? If yea, How ſhall any other man reſt ſecure from their Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, who invade one another; and rob amongſt themſelves; being empowred to do ſo by every one elſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So</hi> alſo;
<note place="margin">Vſurpation over the Laws.</note> 
               <hi>whether or no,</hi> Both Houſes have invaded and trampled down the Laws of the Land; heretofore celebrated, as the moſt glorious Birthright of the Engliſh people, above all other Nations? If no; why is not ſatisfaction given or endeavoured to the honoured writings of that <hi>Death-Defyer Juſtice Jenkins?</hi> who aſſuredly hath a very good Cauſe; or elſe is a very unadviſed Man. And certainly if his Cauſe proves good; He deſerves to have his Statue erected in all Places of publick Judicature, and Societies of the Laws; yea his Memoriall in each Heart; and his Picture in each private Houſe, which with the hazard of his head, he endeavours to defend from violence. Do your Lawyers indeed know, that he is an impregnable Defender of thoſe Laws which they pretend to; but fight againſt? If the Laws be not invaded; How comes it to paſſe, that it is generally even in all mens mouthes; that nothing is now ſo puniſhed, as keeping of the Laws? And that as the greateſt of all guilts? But if yea; and the Laws be indeed trampled down; who ſhall dare to be ſo undaring, as to prefer
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110811:2"/>before them (by which he glories to hold all three) either <hi>Liberty, Propriety,</hi> or <hi>Life?</hi> Againſt any Oppoſers whatſoever; under any lawfully retriving the ſame? Which Laws if they be not in force; How comes one man to exerciſe lawfull Authority over another? If they be; Is not the Murderer murthered, who is puc to death, by virtue of a Commiſſion under the preſent Broad Seal? And the whole Land involved in the guilt of nocent, as well as of innocent Blood? And are not they deepeſt in that gulf, who ſit &amp; judge againſt the Laws?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> it is far more conſiderable; <hi>whether or no,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vſu pation againſt the King.</note> they have invaded the <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Royall.</hi> Inaſmuch as the Lawmaker muſt needs be of more ſacred Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then the Law it ſelf. In the violations of particular Statutes, the Fruits of Juſtice are either ſpoiled or ſtolne; or elſe a Branch is murdered: In the Body of the Laws, the Body of the Tree of Juſtice is hewen down: But in the <hi>Regall Authority,</hi> the Tree is plucked up by the Roots. Neither do the Laws of the Land acknowledge any other Root, then the King. If it be otherwiſe, why then are not all our Law-books burnt? yea Mr. <hi>Pims and St. Johns Speeches?</hi> If it be ſo; Alas poore Rootleſſe, Headleſſe People! Amongſt whom nothing is viſible, but devouring Crowes, or devoured carkaſſes! And doubtleſſe, it is not more unnatural to have no Head, then it is monſtrous and dangerous to have many. By what name ſhall we now be called? Is any wretched enough for us? What ever they ſhall Anabaptiſe themſelves into; they muſt forbear the ancient and moſt glorious of all their Titles: unleſſe to do quite contrary to both the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and Example of CHRIST, muſt denominate them Chriſtians. CHRIST hath layed his (now) no unjuſt Injunction upon us; which he hallowed and made commendable, yea glorious unto us, as a moſt High and precious Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern (ſaith St. <hi>Peter</hi>) for our neceſſary imitation; In ſuffering under (without reſiſtance of) a moſt unjuſt Tyrant. In whom their wretched Plea againſt his noble Army of Martyrs of the pure Primitive Church (blaſting of their bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Reſolutions) could take no place. Certainly in him, <hi>Non deerant vires.</hi> He had ſtrength to reſiſt: The Martyrs abhorred to try whether they had or no. Thus it behoved Him to enter, and them to follow him into glory. And other Defence then this, or Flight; Chriſtian Religion, ſince it came down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, never taught: yea never did not teach againſt; though againſt the moſt barbarous (yea) of Heathen Tyrants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If this he otherwiſe;</hi> Is there not ſo much conſcionable charity left,
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwered by Mr. <hi>Marſhall.</hi>
               </note> as to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Book of Doctor <hi>Hammond</hi> concerning <hi>Reſiſtance of the lawfull Magiſtrate under coloun of Religion?</hi> How comes it to paſſe, that their Grand Champion hath now croſſed his cudgels? Muſt the preſent Militia, and Councell of War, for ever want their engaged Advocate? With what contentment can his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors look upon Him? Or with what forchead can he look upon them, who for theſe divers yeers, hath returned no Anſwer to that Tract (in that Book of Dr. <hi>Hammonds</hi>) which begins thus. <hi>There is nothing more uningenuous or unjust, then Mr. Marſhals,</hi> &amp;c. Muſt our undoing be the onely Argument to rectifie our erroneous underſtandings? And muſt ſuch—men (contrary to the Doctrine and Deaths of Chriſt and his Apoſtles) barely ſay us out of our Religion and Allegiance; which, and by which we have ſolemnly ſworn? Surely we could be content to have kept our eſtates, or now voluntarily to reſigne, could they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110811:3"/>bring us but one good Argument, to demonſtrate a new way to Heaven. In the mean time till this pity be afforded us, we ſhall be learning to forget our inconſiderable loſſes; yea (and if need be, bloodie croſſes; while we have an eye towards him, whom God hath made ſo like to both the <hi>Royall Davids;</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> who was conſtrained to dwell with <hi>Meſhech;</hi> and the <hi>Son,</hi> who not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of his own, an houſe to put his head in, was led away into the wildernes, to be tempted out of his kingdom by the unreaſonable Propoſitions of the Grand Tempter. Since (for the raiſing of pious emulations in other Breaſts; all of us not having capability of being tempted like him alone) even viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity it ſelf, hath already given him Livery and Seiſin of the eight Bleſſedneſſes in <hi>Matt.</hi> 5. As, for his Dominion upon Earth, GOD hath united in him all the Titles of the Brittains, Saxons, Danes and Normans. And ſurely were the Angels of GOD to chooſe us a King; fairer virtues and richer Chriſtianity, could not preſent themſelves, to their choiſe, from out his whole Dominions, then what are eminent in himſelf. Wherefore <hi>weep not for him, you Daughters of Jeruſalem; but weep for your ſelves and your Children:</hi> And forget not to bewail in your prayers, thoſe who obdurately (as yet) perſiſt in the heating of this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace to the hight; which can but purifie, not burn him. For our GOD is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But yet there remains a more dreadfull conſiderable then all theſe;
<note place="margin">Vſurpation againſt God.</note> whether or no,</hi> (in all, or any of this) there hath been any uſurpation, againſt or without GOD? This is moſt evident, <hi>That</hi> not Any thing which was once Nothing, can have any juſt power, but by the Creators gift, who made it ſomething. And this is moſt certain, <hi>That</hi> there is no new Covenant, Grant, or Demiſe, from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,
<note place="margin">Scripture principles.</note> to be expected with mankind; ſince the date of the New Teſtament. <hi>That</hi> unto GOD (and not the People) in both the Teſtaments, is aſſerted, the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Kingſhip over his whole Creation. <hi>That</hi> for the regulating thereof, there can be no juſt Authority, but what is inſtituted and ſet in order by GOD. <hi>That</hi> in neither of the Teſtaments GOD hath appointed, or permitted, or ſo much as mentioned any other Form of Government then Monarchicall. <hi>That</hi> in both the Teſtaments GOD hath conſtituted and declared for Government by Kings, and onely them: As the onely viſible Images of his <hi>One</hi> Majeſtie; and the onely Supreme and irreſiſtible Adminiſtrators of his Divine Power, for the Generall Externall Government of the whole Earth: ſince Mankinde can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect, dare not endure, that his dreadfull Self ſhould deſcend to govern us by his immediate Preſence. <hi>That</hi> GOD hath conſtituted in the Family the Honour of the Father; In the Kingdom the glory of the King; As viſible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and ſenſible ſteps for Remembrancers unto us of our Duty to him: And as Touchſtones of the Honour, which we give unto the univerſall Parent and King of the whole world. <hi>That</hi> the glory and riches of Kings, hath ever been promiſed as Gods moſt glorious earthly bleſſing; and looked upon as the greateſt Admeaſurement of his temporall favours to any Nation: <hi>And that</hi> GOD hath recorded to his own glory, the magnificence of Kings; and never found fault (in them alone) with any ſumptuouſneſſe, which under him they have uſed to make themſelves eminent in the eyes of man. <hi>That</hi> under GODS viſible Repreſenter, and by obedience unto him, Man onely can have Title to the Bleſſings of the Earth.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:110811:3"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>That</hi> it is the <hi>Prerogative of God</hi> to be the ſole Inquiſitor and puniſher of thoſe his Vicegerents, <hi>To reſtrain the Spirit of Princes; And to turn their Hearts,
<note place="margin">Gods earthly Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</note> as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him. That</hi> he who hath promiſed to obedient People good Kings, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved unto Himſelf Power to puniſh wicked people by wicked Princes. <hi>That</hi> it is the Title of CHRIST (which he hath dearly bought) to be <hi>the onely Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate; King of Kings; and Lord of Lords.</hi> So that not all Mankinde without uſurpation upon His Royall Prerogative, may preſume againſt or upon that Dignity; which is onely his to beſtow and cenſure. Under whom Chriſtian Kings are aſſerted into a more glorious Condition then any other Princes whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That to be the Lord of hoſts</hi> is the ſole <hi>Prerogative of GOD.</hi> Which if it be ſo; And that no Humane Authority may take away the life of any,
<note place="margin">The Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</note> whom GOD hath created after his own <hi>Image: the Iſſues of life and death being ever in the hands of the Creator;</hi> And that he muſt be more then <hi>Mans Brother,</hi> who may preſume to do thus: Then may no Man, but empowered from GOD by the warranty of his Commiſſion, either in Peace, or by warre ſhed the blood of man. And if GOD hath given this Divine Authority unto Kings, and unto none elſe,
<note place="margin">The guilt of Blood, where.</note> upon Record in his Regiſtry: Then it appears where lyes the guilt of all the Blood ſpilt in the fields, or ſtrangled upon the Tree, in theſe dayes of calamity. If they have any plea in this particular, let them produce it; We find the Power of the Sword throughout the whole current of holy Scripture, committed unto Kings and to none elſe. If the Scriptures be ſilent concerning their claim; then it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears who are the uſurpers upon GOD, to <hi>take the Sword,</hi> which muſt be given or not medled with. Then who are the Blaſphemers of GOD and the King: who the miſerable <hi>Sheme'is,</hi> that curſe the Lords Anointed <hi>David,</hi> with the loud crying imputation, of being A Man of Blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If theſe things be ſo;</hi> then it behoveth every man, timely and ſadly to bethink himſelf, how far he hath been an agent, aſſiſtant, or conſentient herein:
<note place="margin">Who In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries.</note> yea how far he hath not been an oppoſer of this wretched Sacriledge, committed againſt the Almighty Creator, yea Redeemer of mankind! who is able to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh all that rob him; but will moſt ſeverely, thoſe that rob him of his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative. But eſpecially thoſe who ſtile themſelves the Aſſembly of Divines, and their ſubordinate Pulpiteers: who (as <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> did) lead on all theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, with <hi>The Name of the Lord.</hi> But chiefly Mr. <hi>Marſhall,</hi> who led on the Cauſe; but ſeems to take no care for the bringing of it off. <hi>And if this be not the Caſe;</hi> they may not be accounted worthy of any crumme of their own, much leſſe of other mens bread, if they do not vindicate the two Houſes; clear themſelves from the imputation of being the publick Incendiaries; and free themſelves from the generall curſes of the poore ſuffering and exhauſted people.</p>
            <p>But in the next place. <hi>If the Mr. of the Houſe be called Belzebub; can or may the ſervant think to eſcape?</hi> If GOD be uſurped upon,
<note place="margin">Vſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the Church.</note> ſhall any man marvell if his Church be ſo uſed? in the prophanation and robbing of all the Houſes of GOD in the Land! But will they indeed cauſe that which we ſuppoſe to be the <hi>daily Sacrifice to ceaſe?</hi> And in the roome thereof <hi>ſet up the Abhomination of Deſolation?</hi> Are not they of the other belief bad enough, to be ſuppoſed to have tender Conſciences? And will they not vouchſafe to juſtifie themſelves; or to rectifie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110811:4"/>us,
<note place="margin">The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</note> for whom alſo CHRIST dyed? Let their Rabbi's (to their Honour) ſhew us, who never heard, that ever there was (untill theſe dayes) a Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted upon the face of the Earth, without a publick Liturgie! That ever God was ſo diſhonoured, as to have his publick worſhip entruſted to the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or wickedneſſe of all preſumers! It will be ſuppoſed (till the contrary be made apparent) that the preſent out-caſt Liturgy contains the Flowers, and Marrow of all the Liturgies of the pure Primitive Ages; cleanſed from the weeds and rottenneſſe, which the envious man, in the worlds declining times, had powred forth into the Earth Otherwiſe, why do they not caſt out of their Creed the Article of the <hi>Catholick Church;</hi> if we have nothing to do with that which was before us?</p>
            <p>And why do they not ſatisfie the poore offended people;
<note place="margin">Directory Religion.</note> complaining that their whole Religion is now become ridiculous or odious: As being turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Pulpit-juſtlings: or elſe praying or giving of thanks for the effuſion of the blood of their Chriſtian Brethren; and for the encreaſe of Hereſies, Schiſmes, Rebellion, Robberies, &amp;c? And that it is now come to paſſe, that we have ſuch a Religion, as we ſhould have weather; if every mans wiſh might be heard, and every Almanack-maker made a true Prophet: yea, that they put upon GOD ſuch a Service, that it is impoſſible for him to remain One and the ſame, and to accept of it. That were he never ſo gracious, his Almightineſſe cannot grant all their requeſts: For that there is not one Congregation, whoſe prayers (if it were poſſible for them to be all of one minde) are not contrary to the prayers of many.</p>
            <p>For GODS Cauſe, let there be ſomething wherein all Iſrael may (which they ought) as one man,
<note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, and the Lords Prayer.</note> joyn in the worſhip of the One GOD; otherwiſe why do they not put out that part of the Article, <hi>The Communion of Saints?</hi> But ſince the Lords Prayer is reprobated, what can be ſaved? Did not he who is the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Father know? or would not he whoſe charity dyed for his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, take care for what was abſolute; when he appointed his Diſciples, that when ever they prayed, they ſhould ſay, <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. Is any thing that is made by GOD himſelf unperfect? or were they while the Bridegroom was with them novices in reſpect of us? Did not he teach them then to pray in the Spirit, when he taught them ſo to pray; and bade them alwayes to do ſo? or did he not provide againſt our pretended Spirits, when he forbade them Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tologies; the fruits of unpremeditated vain bablings? And is not this all the hazardous publick Service (worſe then none) wherewith the moſt high and moſt deſerving Majeſty muſt (caſually every where) be contented, or none? Muſt he be forced from all his viſible Temples here on Earth, into his dwelling place in Heaven? Which as it gave the faſhion to <hi>Moſes, Solomons</hi> and to our materiall Churches, So ought it in the daily one Service thereof, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe unto ours, that his great Name may be hallowed; and his Monarchicall will, ſo done on Earth, as it is in his exemplary Temple in Heaven. In a word, why do they not Aſſemble to the Anſwering of Dr. <hi>Taylors.</hi> Book concerning Set Prayer?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But yet further then this;</hi> it is conſiderable, <hi>whether or no,</hi> they take the courſe (as with the ſouls of many thouſands condemned alive) ſo for the ſtrangling
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110811:4"/>(before the wombe) of all the ſouls of all ſucceeding Generations in this Land? For if this be a true principle, which was delivered for ſuch a one,
<note place="margin">Poſterity undone.</note> by the Grandees and leading men of that ſide, in the Conference at Hampton Court, that no Sacrament can be adminiſtred, but by the Conſecration of a lawfull Miniſter, <hi>(i.)</hi> In our Engliſh Liturgy Prieſt. Then apparent it will eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be: no Biſhop, no Prieſt: no Prieſt, no Sacrament; (now little uſed, and leſſe regarded.) And then, no Sacraments, no Church: no Church, no ſalvation. <hi>That</hi> unto the Biſhop, and to the Biſhop alone, is committed the Authority of ſending Labourers into GODS Vineyard, for the continuance of a viſible Church of CHRIST, upon Earth, until his coming hither again. <hi>That</hi> uſurping in matters Eccleſiaſtical, againſt or without them (yea when the Ark of GODS Church doth indeed totter) is the dreadfull and deſtructive ſin of Schiſme: which St. <hi>Jer:</hi> ſaith is more abhominable then Murther, Adultery, &amp;c. <hi>That</hi> Biſhops are the men whoſe perpetuitie (for the perpetuating of his Church) the GOD of Truth hath ſolemnly ſworn, will be ſeaſonably proved when GOD ſhall vouchſafe us a free and lawfull <hi>Synod:</hi> ſuch a one as without the ſtain of Chriſtianity, his people may joyfully own. In the mean time, why do not our Pretenders afford a Reply to Dr. <hi>Edw: Boughens</hi> Book? Will they eat his bread, and vouchſafe him neither an Alms, nor an Anſwer?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The taking away alſo of Biſhops Votes</hi> may be taken into conſideration:
<note place="margin">Abrogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Votes.</note> which is looked upon as a taking away of the preſence of GOD from the publick Conſultations, in the perſons of them upon whom the glorious character of CHRISTS Mediatorſhip is enſtamped. The Tribe of the Lord being not thought worthy to have any to repreſent them, except (at a ſide Table) thoſe in a ſervile condition, whom the generall voice cals Prieſts of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aſſemblers pluralities. Sacriledge.</note> of their own Conſecration (by their filling of their hands even unto ſcandall unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, &amp;c.) And Schiſmaticks after the order of <hi>Korah.</hi> As alſo the <hi>ſin of Sacriledge,</hi> which was not by the Apoſtle; thought of inferior rank to the ſin of Idolatry. It being forbidden in the ſame Commandment, and the poſitive part thereof: <hi>viz.</hi> Thou ſhalt not worſhip with thy body, nor ſerve with thy goods, graven images; for I am a jealous God: they belong, and I will have them without any rivall payed unto me. And the offences againſt theſe (to wit, the honour with bodily worſhip, or conſecration of goods to any falſe god; or the robbing of me in either) I will vindicate upon the third and fourth generation of thoſe who ſhall voluntarily perſiſt in theſe defiances of me. For certainly GOD is not ſuch a GOD, as to be jealous over, and threaten the want of that, which he will not have. If (as <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.28.) <hi>Every devoted thing,</hi> be (in the preſent tenſe) <hi>moſt holy unto the Lord:</hi> yea (as the Text implyes) an <hi>Anathema</hi> to the uſurper of it; as was <hi>Achans</hi> wedge which brought all Iſrael under the ſcourge of GOD. And if <hi>Ananias</hi> and his wife, devoting all, but keeping back part (whereas without ſin, they might otherwiſe have kept all, it being their own) were ſet forth as deadly examples of GODS jealous wrath in this kinde: Then, what can be thought of them, who fly upon that which was never theirs; but conſecrated out of the magnificence of well affected Princes; And which the Doners themſelves might not have recalled. So that Sacriledge is a ſin generally and highly concernent of a whole Nation; The
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110811:5"/>innocent and nocent: eſpecially if it bear the face of a publick Act. In which point, ſerious men conceive, that we now ſmart for the violations of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And truly it is conſiderable;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Spirit of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</note> that, in the times of ſuch generall impiety, it is juſt with God (as he had foretold of the laſt dayes) to permit the Spirit of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt (which in plain Engliſh ſignifieth an oppoſer of GODS Anointed, Kings and Prieſts) to ſeat it ſelf in the Houſe of GOD: and intermedling in ſacred things (without GODS Call or Commiſſion) to uſurp Authority; <hi>As GOD, over all that is called GOD</hi> (as Kings and chief Prieſts were ſundrie times in the Book of GOD) yea patiently (for a time) to endure their uſurpations againſt himſelf; who indeed is <hi>All that ought to be worſhipped:</hi> permitting in his jealouſie the trampling down of his Ordinances: Who had conſtituted the King to conſult the Prieſt, in all points of his Service; and by his deſignation to Act and Enact: And had exemplified this generall and eternall Rule, in the ſtory of pious <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. appointing ſeverally <hi>the chief Fathers of Iſrael the Prieſts and Levites, for the judgements of the Lord and controverſies in Religion;</hi> And conſtituting <hi>over them Amariah the high Prieſt, over all of them in all matters of the Lord;</hi> As <hi>Zebadiah</hi> the Chancellor, <hi>over all, in all matters of the King</hi> or Kingdom. BUT I PROCEED TO THE CAUSES, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And here leaving ſecret things to God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secret things to God.</note> I ſhall without peremptorineſſe of cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, onely mention, what conſcientious men have reckoned, as in an high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree contrary to the revealed Word of GOD. As firſt the ſin of Sacriledge, act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the dayes of our Fathers in the Reign of <hi>Hen:</hi> 8. continued and increaſed ever ſince. Secondly, the eaſineſſe of our Princes (incited by the fancifull im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of this Nation) in ſending Aſſiſtance to the Subjects of forreign Princes, up in Arms againſt their Soveraigns.</p>
            <p>But there is enough viſible, for the ſtirring up of this great Tempeſt of GODS wrath.
<note place="margin">Generall cauſes of out wo.</note> The proud full Sea of our late peace and plenty. One wave ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging againſt another, and all of them againſt goodneſſe. Wickedneſſe warring againſt wickedneſſes, but chiefly againſt GOD, his Church, and Religion; againſt Man, Society and Honeſty. The <hi>prophanations</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the <hi>religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onſneſſe</hi> of <hi>prophanation.</hi> The Angel of light in black; and the Angel of darknes in white. The Teacher taught, and the Feeder ſtarved. <hi>Sodom</hi> brought into the Body of the Land, and leanneſſe into the ſoul. Fulneſſe and want at the ſame inſtant, both in their extremities. The generall deſolation, wrought by Prodigality on the one hand, and Covetouſneſſe on the other: both deſtroying all beſides, and pining of themſelves. The naturall unnaturalneſſe of hatred; and the hatefulneſſe of ſelf-love. The delicacies and uncleanneſſe of Luſt. Fraud and falſhood got into the places of Truth and Honeſty; and they turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out into the others ſeats. The pride of thoſe who knowing not themſelves, think they know all things, and that they may meddle with any thing, be it never ſo ſacred. The ſervile and idle bulie-headedneſſe of this Nation, affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out-landiſh faſhions for their Religion alſo. Without whoſe <hi>Apes</hi> and <hi>Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks,</hi> we were once unlikely to have had acquaintance with theſe hard names of Presbyterian. Independent, or Warre. But theſe things ſuperadded to the naturall incivility of ungovernable Northern robuſtuouſneſſe and intracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110811:5"/>may ſeem fuell ſufficient to enrage the flame againſt us: And the next conjoyned unto theſe will bring it home into our Houſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt may ſeem,</hi> an univerſall loathing of the providentiall ordinances of GOD,
<note place="margin">Particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities in the Church.</note> and a ſenſuall doting upon the wiſdom of Man (which the Apoſtle cals <hi>Divilliſh.) Hating of Dominions, and ſpeaking evill of Dignities.</hi> In the Church, itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ears, and fiery tongues; but numbneſſe and froſt otherwiſe in the whole Man. Every man eſteeming himſelf too good for the rank wherein GOD hath placed him, aſpiring to teach his Teachers; to ſhear, yea as far as the ſwords of their mouthes could reach, to butcher their Shepherds. Following and crying up thoſe <hi>Hirelings,</hi> who could with greateſt volubility decry thoſe whom GOD had ſet over them. Here, as in the weakeſt place, the miſchief be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan. Firſt, no Biſhop, then no King. But long it was before this Monſter durſt ſhew his teeth. The deluded People ſerved an hard Apprentiſhip in unbelief of this. The King himſelf could not perſwade them, that their Liberty and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety would be loſt with his Prerogative: both enſuing the ruines of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So in the State alſo;</hi> the King (of GODS own inſtitution) became layd aſide; and a conſtitution of humane wiſdom, ſet up in his Place and Power. <hi>For</hi> no man can affirm, that GOD (whoſe are all the Kingdoms of the Earth,
<note place="margin">The ruine of the Church more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictive to the State, then to in ſelf.</note> and whoſe Prerogative it is to ſet up, and pull down his own Deputies) did ever conſtitute any other Government, but Monarchicall. <hi>And this</hi> no man can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that GOD is able, hath promiſed, yea performed an hundred fold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, to each man, who in obedience, to his Ordinance hath ſuffered as a <hi>Chriſtian. That</hi> for his Churches ſake, He hath reproved even Kings; much more will he thoſe who aſſume that power which is ſacred, and his, to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves without his Commiſſion. <hi>That</hi> the Church in the Red Sea is in comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſafetie: perſecuting Aegyptians are drowned in it. <hi>Yea, that</hi> under CHRIST, we owe the Religion which we have, unto the ſufferings of thoſe, whoſe doctrine, diſcipline and worſhip the world now accounts folly; ſo far forth, that it may be doubted, whether if the Church had wanted perſecuters, it had not now wanted Members. And certainly he is a very evill man, whom the badneſſe of the times hath not made better. And ſurely it concerneth the glory of GOD to meet with man in his own kinde, and to make him to ſee to the full, the folly of that wiſdom, which makes him eſteem himſelf never free enough, till he have caſt off his yoke, whoſe ſervice onely is his perfect freedom. Which now he may if he will: One yeer of this Jobilee having coſt the Land more beloved pelf, then all it's Kings have drawn from it ſince the Conqueſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So that in this place it is conſiderable, whether or no,</hi> our preſent miſery was not then enacted, when the King (by humane ordinance,
<note place="margin">The firſt foundation of theſe our miſeries.</note> but never by Divine) was debarred from looking into his Subjects purſes, without conſent in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament? By which means Kings, eſpecially uſurpers, for ſuch pottage as hath been preſented to them, have been neceſſitated to ſell their Birthrights <hi>[origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally GGDS.]</hi> Which the preſent King <hi>[in part denying]</hi> was enforced to break off a former Parliament, and to Declare againſt the uſurpation, irreligion, and injuſtice thereof; And withall, to make uſe of a ſmall part of the Prerogative, which God had given him. Which the Factious having blaſted amongſt the generality, too well loving their purſes; their policy was by ſiniſter means, at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110811:6"/>home and abroad (both in <hi>Scotland</hi> &amp; <hi>France</hi>) to bring him into ſuch ſtreights, as might force a Parliament from him, for them to play their prizes in. But now the truth of this late unſufferable Court flattery, is at length made clear, by thoſe who at Preſent ſit at the Helme. And now it is no flattery to proclaim for them, that where the Soveraign Authority is, there the lives and liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods of all muſt be at command. And yet ſtill the queſtion ſticks, whether the wiſdom of GOD or Man be beſt to be truſted?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In order to theſe followed on;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe.</note> the univerſall bent of the people (in many places) blindly led on, by thoſe whoſe ſpirit of oppoſition commended for the onely Patriots) to chooſe none but ſuch for this preſent Parliament. The Serpenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine policy, diligence and activity of the Faction, prevailed againſt the care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe of the many of the better ſort, and the few of the beſt. So that in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places men were elected not ſo fit for that employment, as peradventure for other Advancement. So that it is here conſiderable, whether it doth not concern the ſleepers to bewail their former neglects; and to take care (if GOD have not decreed the utter ruine of their ill ſought Liberty) that they be not out-witted, and out-acted by thoſe who are in their generation wiſer then themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The idle City mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude fitto be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on.</note> this Parliament being met, and that in a place fitting for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of the Contrivers; they had their deſire, relying upon the multitude of the <hi>Plebs urbica,</hi> whoſe wantonneſſe and idleneſſe had made buſie-bodies; and whoſe naturall weakneſſe or wickedneſſe had made deteſters of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and virtues of thoſe, whom GOD had raiſed up amongſt them, and ſet in his own place over them. The Ringleaders knowing themſelves to be thus backed, neglecting the buſines of His Majeſty (by whoſe Authority they met) firſt fell on work againſt the peoples (the Electors) Priviledge; caſting out of doores, or out of countenance, all thoſe whom they could not bring into the ſame exceſſe with themſelves, though by the people preſented unto the King, to be by him inveſted in as high Authority as any of them. This beginning, with the like continuance hath brought upon you, that which you now ſee and feel: which no Chronicle ſhall be able to repreſent to you and yours. My Letter preſumes not on the particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But yet to ſome,
<note place="margin">The two Houſes whether free.</note> it may ſeem worthy the conſideration; whether or no,</hi> the preſent two Houſes be <hi>free;</hi> that is, <hi>free</hi> from force? If they be not, why without more ado are not we free from them? <hi>Sit liber Dominus qui volet eſſe meus.</hi> And it is an heavy judgement of GOD, that Servants ſhould rule over a People. If they be at this preſent (to let paſſe former writings) why is not the <hi>Hiſtory of Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency</hi> confuted?
<note place="margin">Sundry ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</note> If they affirm their Freedom, we have multitudes of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for their ſolution. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If they be free and wiſe, why doth one and the ſame Body alter continually into contrarieties? And thoſe in things (at leaſt) mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, whereof if one be good, the other muſt of neceſſity be bad! At the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Parliament <hi>Scandalous writings and Petitions</hi> were juſtified by a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree,
<note place="margin">Petitions and free writings.</note> that it was Parliament time, and all Petitions were to be received, and all free writers protected. But now it deſerves death, to Petition; and little leſſe to uſe that conſcionable advice, which the Laws of GOD command us, for the ſnatching our of the fire, thoſe whom we ſee in danger. If the former was Liberty, what by the Rule of Contraries is the latter? And what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110811:6"/>of the reſolution of holy <hi>Job?</hi> If his Adverſary ſhould write a book againſt him, to binde it to his Soul? But by this, they have hindred many wholſome Books from being written; more from being publiſhed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But not to mention the multitudes too well known to the moſt. At firſt <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> was declared againſt; and the <hi>Noble Strafford</hi> put to death,
<note place="margin">Arbitrary power.</note> not for acting, but for a ſurmiſed intending of it. Now nothing but <hi>Arbitrary power</hi> is practiſed: yea and that in the hands of ſuch Committee-men, as ſhame it ſelf is aſhamed of.</p>
            <p n="3">3. At firſt, the <hi>Birthright</hi> of the Subject, the <hi>Laws of the Land</hi> were cried up.
<note place="margin">The Laws</note> But now Birthright and life it ſelf is forfeited for obedience to them: And all the uſe that is made of the pretence of them, is by that to commit and protect Sacriledge, Treaſon, Murther, Rapes, Robberies, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. At firſt, Arms were taken up to reſcue the King from his evill Councell: to bring him into the deſired embraces of his loyall Parliament:
<note place="margin">For King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> And the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of him a moſt glorious Prince. Now they have him, nothing is more dreaded or abhorred, then his preſence amongſt them. He become like the holy and juſt One, betrayed by <hi>Judas,</hi> impriſoned for his too good Deeds: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of Treaſon. <hi>Barabbas</hi> preferred to be ſet at liberty, before he be heard. With a multitude of like inconſiſtencies and impieties: as many as the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions amongſt us, and as glorious.</p>
            <p>BUT AMONGST ALL THE MEANS that have been uſed for the conſummating of theſe our ſinfull miſeries;
<note place="margin">Their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull means. Pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence of Religion.</note> none have been more diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and odiouſly contrary to the unchangeable GOD of Truth and Peace, then that <hi>Religion</hi> (which enjoyneth us under pain of damnation, not to reſiſt, that is, not to uſe Defenſive Arms againſt him (in the ſingular number) unto whom GOD hath committed his Sword) that <hi>Religion</hi> (I ſay) ſhould be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into the condition of an incendiary, and made to heat the fire of hell for thoſe whom CHRIST ſhed his blood for; <hi>That</hi> that ſhould be now truth, which is point blank contrary to the way which GOD put us in. So that if GOD be true, <hi>One and the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever:</hi> the contrary way muſt lead to the contrary place.</p>
            <p>The main Arts uſed in this kinde were chiefly two. The one, againſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion eſtabliſhed: the other for the plauſible eſtabliſhing of their own fancles. The firſt was wrought by the odious aſperſion of Popery, by them caſt upon the King, and his loyall Adherents; upon the Biſhops, and their religious Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers. But of this ſmoak onely Time hath cleared the Stage:
<note place="margin">Imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</note> And it will dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly further make good, that that which was ſuſpected, by weak men, was indeed the onely way for the firm eſtabliſhing of our Religion, againſt the errors and innovations of Popery.</p>
            <p>For the King;
<note place="margin">The King.</note> no words are honorable enough for the pourtraying of his moſt glorious invincible conſtancy; and his moſt patient Chriſtian wiſdom; yea themſelves were not cloſe enough to keep from the publick view ſome of his private Letters taken in his Cabinet,
<note place="margin">His friends</note> wherein he unboſomed himſelf to his moſt virtuous Queen. By which barbarous act, they helped to defile this their own Project For his Adherents who like to His, and Him their <hi>Moſes; choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuffer afflictions with the people of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> The Almighty will be their pay maſter: And if there be univerſities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110811:7"/>and Learning enough, they are not like altogether to be forgotten in this world.</p>
            <p>For the Biſhops and their Order; they are that which is moſt feared and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Papiſts.
<note place="margin">Biſhops &amp;</note> From which both Order and Perſons (yea of thoſe who have been worſt uſed at home) themſelves who ſmart being Judges, they have received their mortall blows. No, they muſt be men of other parts and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples (then the preſent pageantry) who muſt maintain the Cauſe of GOD and his Church againſt that learned and veterane Adverſary.
<note place="margin">Book of Common Prayer.</note> And for the Book of Common Prayer, that is a thing moſt deteſted by them: who ſuffer none (who may come to Sermons) to be preſent at that. But for the others Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Pulpittings: they are their joy, ſcorn, and laughter.</p>
            <p>For the reſt of the perſecuted Clergie,
<note place="margin">The Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy.</note> Experience hath indifferently well undeceived the people, that the imputation was, as falſe in it ſelf, ſo dangerous to them. I ſhall inſtance but in one, who was of many (if not of all others) moſt publickly clamoured againſt. Dr. <hi>Coſins</hi> by name (whoſe Devotions it may be will come into better eſteeme) He whom no deſpight could move or ſhake, though in exile, and in the thickeſt of thoſe our Adverſaries, ſtands as an impregnable fortreſſe; in publick and private, by Tongue and Pen, againſt the learned Jeſuites, and others; juſtifying that faith which under his Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> He ever profeſſed. Which I fear nothing either good or bad, can procure one of his Adverſaries here, once to attempt.</p>
            <p>And here it is conſiderable; whether the Jeſuite and Puritan be not like a Map in <hi>plano,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ieſuit and Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane.</note> or an Hoop ſtretched out at length. The ends ſeeming to be at all poſſible diſtance, one from the other: but being reduced to uſe, muſt meet in the breadth of an hair. They both under the title of Religion rob GOD of his Prerogative: the one to enrich the Pope; the other to befool the people: Both uſe the ſame or the like Arguments: and neither do it out of reſpect to them for whom they pretend: but intend to enjoy themſelves, what ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they arreſt for others.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of their Arts under this head, was by a ſpecious name of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<note place="margin">The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note> to ſtrike through the body of Epiſcopacy, into that of Monarchy: which by the inconſiderate people was eaſily ſwallowed for an Act of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. It being readily viſible to thoſe who onely are ſuperficialiſts in the Book of GOD, that entring into Covenant for the better ſervice of GOD, was often celebrated in the Book of GOD. But it was not minded, that there was no ſuch Covenant, or any other then the renewing of that Covenant of GODS own making, through the whole Scriptures: nor that, that ever was publickly attempted againſt, or without the ſupreme Authority; the pride of ſuch an act never having been once heard of amongſt the former Iſrael of GOD. Not obſerving that the matter of this Vow (beſides the uſurpation upon the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine power of the King, whoſe deſtruction appears to have been the principall end thereof) containeth the moſt dreadfull impieties, which ever yet were veiled under the mask of Religion: the cutting off not of the perſons, but of the Office of thoſe unto whom GOD had ſworn Perpetuity: By which (as hath been ſaid) the Church was to have it's continuance: and without which, no Church in any age or place hath been, or can be; and without which no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King can be eſtabliſhed. So that we may put the whole ſtake upon theſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110811:7"/>two Iſſues. 1. Whether GOD hath accepted of any Nationall Covenant, and this other then the renewing of that w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> himſelf made, without the Supreme Authority? Or 2. whether, untill this Age, there hath been any where, at any time any viſible Nationall Church without Biſhops? In which particular, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe GOD come to conſtitute a new, Man cannot. If He had never done it,
<note place="margin">If Power, then Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</note> the authority of the whole Creature, cannot reach to conſtitute a Power. For if it be power (ſaith the Apoſtle) it muſt be Divine; of, and from GGD. In a word, if GOD hath indeed conſtituted, and hath had a Church upon Earth for theſe 1500. years; it, under CHRIST and his Apoſtles, hath been, by, through and under Biſhops. Other faſhion of Church never yet appeared for ſo long; then what this Covenant vows, Root and Branch to deſtroy: and hereby the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall kingdom of GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Mechanicall part</hi> of this our miſery (in the hands of their Engineers,
<note place="margin">2 Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of oud ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> and their not now ſervants) hath been wrought by two main Inſtruments; the wealth of the City, and the defection of the Navy. Upon the former, other Nations looked with envious comfort: As upon the Liver too bigge for the Land, like to enflame and corrupt the ſtrength thereof. Upon the other with dread, as upon the Arms and Legs of this Nation, too long ſinewy and active for them. But which (if Chriſtianity could have ſubdued naturall malice at home and abroad) might have proved the Arſenall of Europe; and have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried our miſeries home to the doores of Chriſtianities foes. Or yet have done better, and have carried Chriſtianity into the Pagan world; which certainly better deſerves it, then we who thus uſe it. <hi>Heu quantum potuit terrae caeli<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri — Hoc quem civiles hauſerunt ſanguine dextrae?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the City,</hi> I ſhall make bold to crave, <hi>whether or no,</hi> that be deniable, which the generall Complaint puts upon you? And <hi>whether or no,</hi> your ſelves conceive,
<note place="margin">The Cities wealth.</note> that (for the greater part) your wealth hath been ſo conſcionably gotten, that there can be ſufficient ground for hopes, that it might be comfortably ſpent? Or this: that the riches of the Country are tranſplanted into the City: and the manners of the City ſent out into the Country? That your pride hath enflamed the whole Kingdom? That your fraud hath impoveriſhed it? That your luxury hath infected it? and your illiberality except to vain glory, and your ſelves) hath ſpoiled, it's ancient Hoſpitality? But (which is the greateſt miſchief) that the contagion of equall wantonneſſe and new fangledneſſe in Religion, hath ſpread it's peſtilence into the veins, and vitals of the whole Nation? That you could find millions for others, but for the King (the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God) you could not find pounds? That you have given ſo much; that you have no power to keep any thing? except by your prudent and ſpeedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation unto your moſt gracious GOD, and your god-like King, by an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Treaty? The mercies of both being like to prove your beſt Staple.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Navy;</hi> they have better Sea-room,
<note place="margin">The Navy Royall.</note> to bethink themſelves (as they have bleſſedly begun) both of their duty, and of the inexplicable good, which by doing of it, they may do to all, and themſelves. They have a GOD (whoſe wonders they ſee in the deep) who hath ſufficient power; they have a King, who hath ſufficient goodnes to reward them, and his glorious Iſſue with them to enoble their religious courage; they have the prayers of all the tryed ones, whoſe Anchor holds through all their Land ſhipwracks; who mourn in their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110811:8"/>ſouls for a time to celebrate their praiſes, when they ſhall have brought full ballaſt, to ſettle an equall Treaty, for the glory of GOD on high, Peace upon our Earth; and good will amongſt men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>NOW CONCERNING THE REMEDY.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Remedies.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt to thoſe who have not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Beaſt; who have not bowed their knees to <hi>Baal,</hi> nor kiſſed him with their mouthes; who have not ſo much as petitioned for any fifth part; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly abandon the thoughts of their juſt proprieties,
<note place="margin">From the world-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing Chriſtian.</note> while the King wants his; &amp; they (here) only want Him, under whom, &amp; by obedience to whom, they onely can call any thing upon GODS Earth their own. To them mine humble ſuit is, that with heavenly ardour they would endeavour more and more to burn out the droſſe of their own frailties; That inſtead of trembling at a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing calamity, they would admire and celebrate the bounty of GOD who hath thought them worthy to ſuffer; and given them ſomething, the deſpiſing of which, might evidence their love to him. That, as truly ſpirituall men, they may underſtand this to be <hi>All things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For it is moſt equall with God, and moſt advantagious to them, that when he ſees maſterleſſe ſins grow to that height,
<note place="margin">From Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Chriſts imitation.</note> that his publick worſhip will not be permitted, in thoſe who aſpire in the greateſt of humane perfections to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent on his Earth the ſervice of his Angels in Heaven; (when his bounty is extended to the greateſt meaſure of the receivers capability; &amp; mans haughty unthankfulneſſe, will thank, truſt to, and magnifie, not his God but himſelf. Then it is moſt juſt with God to provide for his greater glory, ſelect men, who will neither be afraid nor aſhamed to have in them acted over again (for the raiſing up of an holy ſeed in a better generation) the gratefull ſufferings of his Son CHRIST JESUS, and his bleſſed Martyrs in Heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 2ly, <hi>that</hi> you would ſet forth the glory of CHRIST in intenſive prayers, for thoſe who curſe,
<note place="margin">In Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an charity.</note> hate, and perſecute you, according to his example, gloriouſly followed by his firſt (yea whole Army of Martyrs.) Lord lay not this ſin to their charge. In which particular, theſe our times have not altogether proved barren of right Chriſtian deaths in divers ſpecialties, not ever to be forgotten, though not to be expected in the cancels of a Letter.
<note place="margin">Heroicall examples.</note> Moſt eminently the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentry (for many) have an heroick ſampler in the moſt Noble <hi>Earl of Strafford:</hi> the Clergie in the moſt ſublime humility of the <hi>Archbiſhop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Morall duty.</note> who enjoy Crowns elſewhere, and ſhall have trophies here. And yet not to forget our duty for another, as not to ſell our coat to buy a ſword; when ever the King ſhall by himſelf, or lawfull deputation, call for our lives, and liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods: but even then to carry with you thoſe right Chriſtian affections, as did the primitive Chriſtians, when they withheld not themſelves from the warres of their Pagan Emperours. But never ſo to look backwards towards our loſſes; or to our proviſion for thoſe dear hoſtages of our affections, wife or children (whom God hath promiſed us,
<note place="margin">Hating all, for Chriſt.</note> to take for his, while we perſiſt to do our duties to him) but to look forwards towards the glory which is ſet before us, and to the good which we may do to others, in fortifying them, towards the deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all that this world affords, with relation to the next. And yet we ſhall not do ill Chriſtianly to admoniſh our proſecutors; that had the great <hi>Turk</hi> himſelf conquered us (whereas through the preſumption and connivance of the reſpective Committees, ſew or none enjoy a fift part, pretended to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110811:8"/>to wife and children) for 7 <abbr>s.</abbr>-6 <abbr>d.</abbr> a man, &amp; the fourth part of our encreaſe,
<note place="margin">Turkiſh mercy.</note> we might have been ſecure for the reſt; yea and which is more then all the reſt, the <hi>Freedom of our Religion</hi> to boot. <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the others,</hi> who are abundantly the greater part, my Petition to them is;
<note place="margin">Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for the major part.</note> that they would not deſpair, while CHRIST is in Heaven, his Word on Earth, and they have hearts to follow the directions thereof. Let no man ſay it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible: GOD may be importuned and overcome by many hands, by univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall prayers, and amendment: if we can but bring our ſelves to hate all, that ſtands in competition with him. I deſire not to repreſent unto them their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and loſſes, which they are too ſenſible of, and too little of the blood wantonly ſpilt; and the deaths of ſouls more precious. I onely tell them, how for the preſent they may avoid the ſin, and for the future the puniſhment. Which, as concerning their earthly eſtates, cannot be compaſſed, while the Houſes continue their reſolutions. So long, they muſt have an Army, the Army will be maintained, cannot but be inſolent; while no man can account any thing his own which they can take <hi>Covet therefore, what cannot he taken;</hi> And fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the courſe, that may be taken.</p>
            <p>You know,
<note place="margin">From the 2. Houſes own Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</note> As your own duties of Chriſtian Allegiance to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all that is dear unto you: ſo the principle (though in it ſelf moſt falſe and blaſphemous) which being theirs, and that by which they have prevailed againſt you and yours, they may not with colour of honeſty deſert. Which is this; <hi>That the power of Dominion is originally in the People.</hi> Which is a deſperate Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion refuted by the clear Word of GOD, and ſundry Books yet unanſwered. By you they pretend to be entruſted with the government of the Land. And if they have not this Power from you, they have it not otherwiſe by any Law of GOD or Man. And if (as they moſt falſly pretend) you might re-aſſume the Power from the King; then certainly you may from them, to whom GOD nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath, nor you could give them; and ſo their whole title (againſt you) muſt reſt in force: which at firſt they neither did or might pretend; and which every Tyrant would bluſh openly to own.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, you know that you are the major part of the Kingdom (at leaſt 20. to one) whoſe eyes either Religion or irreligious oppreſſion hath opened.
<note place="margin">Petitions undid us.</note> And it is not unknown unto you, how in the beginning of this Parliament (while you ſlept in lazy ſecurity) that Petitions, by the reſtleſnes of a few, were extorted or forged, and preſented in the generall names of the ſeverall Counties, and ſo received, as if they had been Catholick and orthodox: and from theſe <hi>Players</hi> hath proceeded our reall <hi>Tragedy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But here,</hi> I do not wiſh that you ſhould go that way. My ſelf dares not ſo far ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge any authority, which my ſoul eſteems to ſtand in armed oppoſition againſt GOD and his Ordinances. And it is well known, how for this thing the Petitioners of <hi>Surrey,</hi> and the compaſſionate <hi>Watermen</hi> loſt their lives, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any inqueſt upon that blood. How the <hi>Kentiſh</hi> and men of <hi>Eſſex</hi> for the ſame cauſe were proſecuted with cruell warre, and too bloody for Pen and Ink to expreſſe. But (if ſo your ſelves be minded, and you do conceive the foregoing Propoſals worthy of your conſiderations) I could rather Petition you, in a Declarative way, to take unto you; as,
<note place="margin">A Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> the reſolutions of free-born men; ſo chiefly the modeſty, ſobriety, and peaceablenes of Chriſtians: ſo farre forth, that (if it be poſſible) the mouthes of your greateſt Adverſaries may be
<pb facs="tcp:110811:9"/>ſtopped, and they enforced to blame rather themſelves, then the meekneſſe of your ſick liberty, breathing out it ſelf, in the way of religious charity, not of cumultuous and paſſionate Revenge or Hatred. Expreſſing <hi>whether or no</hi> you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended or will endure the <hi>Arbitrary Power of the Houſes;</hi> their levying men and Arms, with <hi>Free quarter, Taxes, Exciſe,</hi> &amp;c. againſt or without the King. <hi>Whether</hi> you conceive this fitting to be done, or that lawfully you may do it? <hi>Whether</hi> the ſubmiſſion you have hitherto yeelded was voluntary or forced? And <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no</hi> (thankfully looking back unto the former bleſſings (under Him en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed) you ought not to Petition the King, and GOD Almighty for him, that He do not (by Treaty or otherwiſe) part with the Militia, or any other part of his Prerogative Royall (which appearing to be GODS) he may not with a ſafe Conſcience, by any voluntary Act acquit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So alſo</hi> further to conſider; whether it be not neceſſary to Petition his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty;
<note place="margin">For a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod.</note> that by his Authority <hi>A Synod</hi> (with all convenient ſpeed) may be called? Such as we may juſtifie before GOD and Man: according to the examples of the ancient Primitive Church: for the compoſing of Controverſies, and the eſtabliſhing of Unity in Religion, and the publick worſhip of GOD. And that all ſorts of Diſputants may be invited, yea encouraged, with freedom and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity to propoſe in writing, their ſeverall Deſires and Reaſons; and thoſe to be entred into the publick Acts to remain upon Record for ever: that all men and Times may ſee not onely what was done, but why, &amp; upon what grounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> in caſe neither Treaty nor Declarations avail, by their default; then to conſider, <hi>whether or no,</hi> it be neceſſary further to Declare, that you do revoke your former Subſtitutions,
<note place="margin">Revocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the pretended power of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</note> whereby the Houſe of Commons pretends in your Names to ſit? And to proteſt againſt their former Acts and Ordinances? And that according to your warranty from the Word of GOD, you have taken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the reſolutions, to deny your ſelves; and comparatively, to <hi>hate wife and children, houſe and lands, trade and traffique, and your own lives alſo,</hi> rather then you will do, or have any thing, towards the maintaining of any, in oppoſition to the Ordinance of GOD; before GOD ſhall pull down all ſtomacks againſt U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, by his plague of famine, which he makes apparent, that he can do it, by this unſeaſonable weather ſent now amongſt us. Since the floods of our blood cannot effect it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo</hi> for the future that (if it ſhall pleaſe GOD to continue you alive to make new Election) you will be as diligent (as others late have been) for the chooſing of men well affected to the Laws,
<note place="margin">Caveats for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</note> peace and order of this Kingdome and that you will pitch upon none, from whom you have not ſufficient evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their valuing of the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance, formerly, and at the preſent of Election,
<note place="margin">No guard, but of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation &amp; Innocency.</note> to have been, and to be by them taken; with ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Bonds and Penalties upon Indentures between you and them, in theſe or the like particulars; and that they will not admit of other Arms or Guards about them (except by voluntary order from the King, if he finds cauſe) then the protection of their own reputation and innocency: whereas nothing but the witchery of that abuſed Name of Parliament could have abuſed you into the ſhame and ſin, which their force hath brought upon your and whoſe Arms would ſoon fail, if the fraud of that name was underſtood. THIS he preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to preſcribe, but with all Chriſtian humility to preſent unto your conſiderations. Beſeeching you not to accept of private whiſperings, or peece meal Anſwers, but to require pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and totall ſatisfaction to theſe; and other your juſt complaints<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And minding of you, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had a Clergy (whoſe neglect he forbears to relate amongſt the cauſes of your miſeries who would have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>orred, that ſuch things ſhould have been objected (for any thing taught or done in their times) and nor have been at all, or ſo anſwered, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
